<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cordial-mediator for accordance of brethren that are of different judgments and wayes of administration in things that concerne the Kingdome of God for repairing of the breach and restoring of the paths for many generations : wherein is proposed the way and means (not to inforce or compell to an outward dissembling, hypocriticall uniformity, which is all that can be inforced unto by humane authority, but) to induce and ingage to a cordiall-uniformity even of soule and spirit amongst all that are truly and really Christians, and to bring them likewise into the same wayes and ministrations in the things of God / written by Ellis Bradshaw.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09682020</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09682020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43990</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43990)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1325:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cordial-mediator for accordance of brethren that are of different judgments and wayes of administration in things that concerne the Kingdome of God for repairing of the breach and restoring of the paths for many generations : wherein is proposed the way and means (not to inforce or compell to an outward dissembling, hypocriticall uniformity, which is all that can be inforced unto by humane authority, but) to induce and ingage to a cordiall-uniformity even of soule and spirit amongst all that are truly and really Christians, and to bring them likewise into the same wayes and ministrations in the things of God / written by Ellis Bradshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 33 [i.e. 36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Lodowick Lloyd, also by Henry Crips and by Thomas Brewster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Christian union.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43990:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43990:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CORDIAL-MEDIATOR, for ACCORDANCE of BRETHREN, THAT Are of different Judgments and wayes of Adminiſtration, in things that concerne the Kingdome of God: For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing of the breach, and reſtoring of the paths for many generations WHEREIN Is propoſed the way and means (not to inforce or compell to an outward diſſembling, hypocriticall uniformity, which is all that can be inforced unto by humane authority, but) to induce and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to a Cordiall uniformity even of ſoule and ſpirit amongſt all that are truly and really Chriſtians; and to bring them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe into the ſame wayes and miniſtrations in the things of God.</p>
            <q>
               <p>For this is the Meſſage that ye have heard from the Beginning, that we ſhould love one another: Not as Cain who was of the Evill one, and ſlew his Brother; and wherefore ſlew he him? becauſe his own works were evill, and his Brothers righteous, <bibl>
                     <hi>1 John 3.11, 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>We are of God: he that knoweth God, heareth us, he that is not of God, heareth not us: hereby know we the ſpirit of truth, &amp; the ſpirit of errour <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Joh. 4.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>If ye love me keep my Commandements, <bibl>
                     <hi>Joh. 14 15, ſee alſo verſ. 16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>He that is of God, heareth Gods words: Ye therefore hear them not, becauſe ye are not of God, <bibl>
                     <hi>Joh. 8.47.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Written by ELLIS BRADSHAW.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Lodowick Lloyd</hi> at the Caſtle in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> alſo by <hi>Henry Crips</hi> at the end of <hi>Popes-head-Alley,</hi> and by <hi>Thomas Brewſter</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls-Church-yard,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43990:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To his Highneſſe <hi>Richard</hi> the now Lord Protector, together with the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the dominions thereunto belonging. May it pleaſe your Highneſſe, together with the Honourable Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here preſent you in the name of God, &amp; of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, with a ſhort Epitomie of that <hi>fiery law,</hi> and that <hi>everlaſting Goſpell</hi> (Deut. <hi>33.2. and</hi> Rev. <hi>14.6.) which</hi> ſhall be <hi>preached to them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, and kinred, and tongue, and people,</hi> and that immediately upon the downfall of Babilon, <hi>ſee verſ. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</hi> as by reading theſe <hi>6</hi> verſes you may plainly ſee, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Angell <hi>flying in the midſt of Heaven, having the everlaſting Goſpell,</hi> &amp;c. The next that followed proclaimed <hi>Babilon is fallen, is fallen,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo the third Angell followeth threatning the Judgment and wrath that ſhould certainly befall <hi>them that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped the Beaſt and his Image, or receive his mark in their foreheads, or on their hands,</hi> ſee verſ. <hi>9, 10, 11, 12.</hi> And that all theſe things are the ſucceſſe or effects or at leſt part thereof upon the 7th Angell ſounding of his Trumpet, <hi>ſee Chap. 11.15.</hi> And that time ſhall be no longer till the miſtery of God be finiſhed, but till the ſeventh Angell ſhould ſound his Trumpet, ſee the Oath of the Angell, <hi>Chap. 10, 5, 6, 7.</hi> And this <hi>14</hi> Chapter being held forth to us as part of
<pb facs="tcp:43990:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> the effects upon the 7th Angells ſounding, as that by reading the Chapters is cleere and manifeſt; I ſhall not need to make any further proof that <hi>Babilon</hi> ſhall fall upon the holding forth of the everlaſting Goſpel. I mean when it is ſo preached and ſo received as the everlaſting Goſpell, for ſuch is the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, it is both a Goſpell <hi>to wit</hi> glad-tidings, and it is the Goſpell, the glad-tidings, <hi>to wit</hi> the only glad-tidings that are everlaſting; to them that dwell on the earth, and therefore ſhall be preached to every na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, kinred, and tongue, and people; <hi>Saying</hi> (more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over) <hi>fear God, and give glory to him, for the hour of his judgment is come: and worſhip him which hath made heaven and earth, and the ſea, and the fountaines of waters,</hi> ſee Chap. <hi>14.6, 7.</hi> And this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is Goſpell, for it is glad-tidings when the hour of his Judgment is come, and his advice is good, to fear God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in regard he is ſaid to ſay it with a loud voyce. It is intimated that it ſhould be more audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſpoken, and more generally heard and received then it had been formerly, and that by all nations, kinreds, tongues, and peoples. And it may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to conſider, that it is ſaid and ſworn by the Angell, that <hi>in the dayes of the voyce of the 7th An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, when he ſhall begin to ſound the miſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed, as he hath declared to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets,</hi> ſee Chap. <hi>10.7.</hi> Not that all ſhould be finiſhed when he ſhall begin to ſound; for in that there is a beginning it implieth a continuance; And it is ſaid alſo that in the dayes of the voyce <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the miſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed: Now how many dayes the voyce of this ſounding ſhall continue it is not eaſily determined, being only held forth in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall number without limitation: But this is certain,
<pb facs="tcp:43990:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> that when he ſhall begin, his ſounding ſhall continue till the miſtery of God be finiſhed.</p>
            <p>Now ſee the firſt effects or what is fully concluded on, and voted in the Church, and by the four and twenty El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders when the 7th Angell begun to ſound <hi>Chap. 11.15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</hi> And it evidently appeareth, that <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this world ſhall certainly become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall</hi> (thenceforth) <hi>reign for ever and ever.</hi> For which there is thanks ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the holy Elders, <hi>becauſe he had taken to him his great power, and had reigned,</hi> and how, <hi>the nations were angry,</hi> &amp;c. ſee and read the verſes, for they doe concern us if we be chriſtians indeed, and not in ſhew only, and that in theſe dayes, and for our great comfort and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in the wayes of God, they are held forth to us. For hath he not begun, hath he not already taken to himſelfe even his great power, and hath reigned amongſt us; Hath he not <hi>given a bannor to them that fear him,</hi> Pſal. <hi>60.4.</hi> Hath he not begun, <hi>and ſhall he not make an end, 1</hi> Sam. <hi>3.12.</hi> Hath he not already <hi>whett his glittering ſword,</hi> and hath not <hi>his hand</hi> already <hi>taken hold of vengeance;</hi> And ſhall he not <hi>fully recompence his adverſaries, and repay them that hate him,</hi> ſee Deuter. <hi>32.40, 41, 42, 43.</hi> And hath he not owned this nation, yea even this of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that as firſt, yea and alſo above others, yea even any nation now under Heaven; And that for his own cauſe ſake, though not for our worthineſſe, but for reſpect to his name, the which through his grace was owned by us againſt his adverſaries; Yea and that by a ſtrong hand, and a ſtretched out arme, many a time giving victory to a few againſt their double number, and that to weake and deſpiſed ones againſt the ſtrong and potent, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our hopes and expectations, or the fears of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and that by ſea and land. And why ſhould we
<pb facs="tcp:43990:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> think that he will repent him for his choice of us before any nation now under heaven. The Apoſtle telleth us <hi>his gifts and callings are without repentance,</hi> Rom. <hi>11.29.</hi> And though he <hi>will oblitterate the names of ſuch out of his book of life</hi> (as he ſaid unto Moſes) <hi>who ſin againſt him</hi> (Exod. <hi>32.32, 33.</hi>) yet <hi>he will be mercifull unto his land and to his people.</hi> And therefore he ſaith: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce oh ye nations with his people, for he will avenge the blood of his ſervants, and will render vengeance to his adverſaries, and will be mercifull to his land and people,</hi> ſee Deut. <hi>32.43.</hi> And of this we may be confident that he that hath begun will certainly make an end, before he break off from us whom he hath owned as a peculiar people in a nationall way, and that above any nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven, as once he did to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old. And will bring us to reſt and ſettlement in ſpite of all oppoſers, either forraine or domeſtick. And he will give <hi>victory on the Lambs ſide, together with them who are the called, &amp; choſen and faithfull. His heart is towards the governors of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>who have jeoparded their lives (to maintaine his cauſe) upon the high places of the field; with</hi> Zebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>and</hi> Napthali, ſee Judges <hi>5.9.18. for they offered themſelves willingly amongſt the people, and have not loved their lives even unto the death,</hi> Rev. <hi>12.11. And therefore rejoyce ye heavens</hi> (that is to ſay ye Churches, militant and triumphant) <hi>and ye that dwell in them, but woe to the inhabitants of the earth, and of the Sea;</hi> (that is to the world) <hi>for the Devill is come downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth that he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> verſ. <hi>12.</hi> to wit, till he muſt <hi>be incloſed in the bottomleſſe pit, that he ſhall not deceive the nations any more till a thouſand years ſhall be fulfilled,</hi> ſee Rev. <hi>20.1, 2, 3.</hi> Yea <hi>woe unto the world becauſe of offences, for</hi> (though) <hi>it muſt needs be that
<pb facs="tcp:43990:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> offences ſhall come, yet woe to that man by whom the offence cometh, ſee</hi> Mat. <hi>18.7.</hi> Doubtleſſe it hath ever been dangerous to <hi>give any offence either to Jew, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, or to the Church of God,</hi> ſee <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>10.32.</hi> but much more now in theſe latter dayes wherein the Lord hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to <hi>avenge his Elect, who cry unto him day and night,</hi> for now he hath begun, he will certainly hold on, and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge them ſpeedily,</hi> as hath been proved before, Luke <hi>18.7, 8.</hi> And therefore it is the advice of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>to take heed that we deſpiſe not one of thoſe little ones, yea one of the leaſt of thoſe little ones that beleeve in him,</hi> and the reaſon is rendred, <hi>becauſe that in heaven there Angels doe alwayes behold the face of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven;</hi> For they are <hi>all miniſtring ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſent forth for the good of them who ſhall be heires of ſalvation;</hi> and will readily accompliſh what the will of God ſhall require them to doe. For they alwayes behold his face to know his will concerning his ſervants, that they might accompliſh it concerning all his Elect over whom they have Charge, <hi>ſee Matth. 18.10. Mark 9.42. Heb. 1.14. Pſal. 103.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if it be ſo much danger to offend but one of the leaſt of thoſe little ones, that beleeve in Chriſt, as that it <hi>were better for him that a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were caſt into the depth of the Sea,</hi> &amp;c. How dangerous is it to offend his Embaſſadors that are ſent unto us in the name of the Lord, for the good of our ſouls; Is it not ſaid, <hi>He that receiveth you recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me, and he that receiveth me receiveth him that ſent me; And he that deſpiſeth you deſpiſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me;</hi> But how few is there in theſe our dayes that regard theſe words, or at leaſt ſo regard them as to caution them as they ought in theſe reſpects. Are not the words of men in
<pb facs="tcp:43990:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> authority as Magiſtrates and Officers, and maſters much more regarded then theſe words of Chriſt. They that are under command, under any authority, either civill or mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, will quickly ſay we are ſo commanded, and we muſt obey elſe it will be worſe for us, we ſhall be turned out of office, or out of our ſervice, or places elſe, or thoſe our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours will be offended with us, and for ſuch like reaſons which in ſuch caſes are good and wiſe, and but our duty, but how few is there that are ſo wiſely ſubſervient to the commands of God, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to take his counſells and admonitions, and lay them to heart, and own them as a rule for regulation of all their wayes. But if you pleaſe to read with ſeriouſneſſe of ſpirit, but this little Treatiſe, you will eaſily perceive how much we are ſhort of obedience, and ſubſerviencie to the commands of Chriſt, yea even the beſt of us all, and ſo what need there is to make it our buſineſſe to indeavour a redreſſe, what in us lyeth, in our places and callings, and to provoke one another to love and good works which are ſo much wanting. And for this end I have directed it to you who are in higheſt authority, though I therein ſpeak not to you only, but to all that are or profeſſe themſelves to be chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans indeed, &amp; not in ſhew only: that you &amp; all ſuch might incourage and induce what in them lieth to a cordiall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of hearts and affections in the wayes of God. For though it is a thing that cannot poſſibly be compelled to by humane authority, yet it much conduceth and helpeth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when the eyes of authority are bent that wayes. The incouragement of authority in well doing, is a ſtrong inducement to the doing of it. And ſo is likewiſe their own example no leſſe available with ingeneous ſpirits, ſee <hi>1 Pet. 2.14.</hi> The Lord grant that you may make it your bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe when you come to deale in matters of religion. To accord our differences as much as may be, and to ſettle
<pb facs="tcp:43990:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> peace both in Church and ſtate, what in you lyeth; And in ſo doing the Lord will aſſiſt you and bleſſe your indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the good of theſe nations to all poſterities: which is the earneſt deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Cordiall Subject</hi> Ellis Bradſhaw.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>I Deſire the Reader to mend theſe <hi>Erratats</hi> following, and to make the reſidue ſence in the reading, <hi>to wit.</hi> Page 6. line 4. for <hi>on</hi> read <hi>or.</hi> Page 8. line 30. for <hi>ſtate</hi> read <hi>ſave.</hi> Page 13. line 26, for <hi>ſmite them hand,</hi> read <hi>ſmite them with the hand.</hi> Page 31. line 4, for <hi>conſecrate</hi> read <hi>conſociate,</hi> and line 26. for <hi>hear</hi> read <hi>heavens,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43990:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A CORDIAL-MEDIATOR, FOR Accordance of Brethren that are of different Judgements, and wayes of Adminiſtration in things that concern the Kingdom of God: For repairing of the breach and reſtoring of the paths for many Generations, as followeth, <hi>to wit.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ELOVED brethren, the end of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I ſhall in few words firſt declare with the grounds thereof before I begin, becauſe I love not prolixity nor would not be miſtaken, <hi>to wit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That all the elect and beloved of God that know one another and in the Judgement of charity account one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſuch <hi>might love</hi> one another <hi>as brethren,</hi> and that <hi>with a pure heart fervently.</hi> See my ground for this 1 Pet. 1.22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all that are in truth, in the light, might ſo <hi>walke in the light,</hi> as to <hi>have fellowſhip one with another.</hi> So <hi>as the blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt might cleanſe us from all ſin.</hi> See my ground for this, 1 John 1.7. And the rather becauſe that <hi>if we ſay that we have fellowſhip with God and walke in darkneſſe, we lye and doe not the truth.</hi> See verſ. 6 <hi>And if we walke in the light we have fellowſhip one with another;</hi> &amp;c. So that we cannot demonſtrate that we have fellowſhip with God and the Lord Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us Chriſt, unleſſe we alſo have fellowſhip one with another. And therefore cannot ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>to wit, And truly our fellowſhip is with the father,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43990:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and with his ſon Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> See ver. 3. Neither can we demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that we <hi>are in the light,</hi> nor that we love God, unleſſe we alſo <hi>love the brethren,</hi> See Chap. 2 9, 10, 11. and Chap. 4.20. <hi>He that ſaith he is in the light and hateth his brother is in darkneſſe, and walketh in darkneſſe, and knoweth not whither he goeth. And if a man ſay I love God, and hateth his brother he is a lyar, for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> From which it appeareth that it is for want either of light or love, or rather both, if we have not fellowſhip one with another. So that we cannot demonſtrate that we are in the light, nor that we love God, nor that we love our brethren, nor that God loveth us, nor that we keep his commandements un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we ſo love our brethren as to have fellowſhip with them: For <hi>this is his command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment that we love one another, and that even ſo, as Chriſt hath loved us,</hi> for this is the manner and meaſure required; as I ſhall further make to appear, from the Law and Teſtimony.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the command of God, Lev. 19.18. <hi>thou ſhalt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge nor bear any grudge againſt the children of thy people, but then ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is alſo the command of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Mat. 22.19. &amp; Luke 10.27, 28. where the command is expreſſed. <hi>This doe and thou ſhalt live,</hi> &amp; John 15.17. <hi>This I command you, that ye love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And the meaſure of this love which is here commanded, is not a ſparing or ſcant meaſure: But <hi>this is my commandement that ye love one another, as I have loved you,</hi> See ver. 12. And ſee alſo John 13 34. <hi>A new commandement I give unto you, that ye love one another, as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one another;</hi> From which it evidently appeareth, that though this commandement is but the ſame in ſubſtance which was from the beginning. Yet in this reſpect it is new and held forth to us under that notion, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it is backed with ſuch an example, <hi>to wit,</hi> the example of Chriſt, who in his own perſon hath exemplified it to us and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us to follow his ſteps, and to love one another, as he hath loved us, binding us hereby to his example in what we are able, and to make it all our marke to aime at as <hi>the marke of the price, of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> So that in reſpect of the meaſure of our love, we ought not to be content with any leſſer
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43990:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> attainement then to <hi>love one another as Chriſt hath loved us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is alſo the <hi>meſſage that we have heard from the beginning that we ſhould love one another,</hi> See 1 John 3 11. <hi>And this is his commandement that we ſhould beleeve on the name of his ſon Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another as he gave us commandement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It is like unto that firſt and great commandement, <hi>to wit. Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoul, and with all thy minde.</hi> See Mat. 23.37, 38, 39, 40. &amp; Deut. 6.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For <hi>upon theſe two commandements hang all the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The end of the commandement is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience and of faith unfained,</hi> (See. 1 Tim. 1.5) <hi>From which ſome having ſwarved, have turned aſide unto vain janglings,</hi> See ver. 6. yea and that in theſe very dayes of ours.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We are exhorted ſeriouſly to ſee <hi>that we love one another with a pure heart fervently.</hi> See 1 Pet. 1.22. It muſt <hi>not be in word and in tongue onely, but in deed and in truth.</hi> 1 John 5.18.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſeriouſly exhorteth us to it, ſhewing us a ſtrong reaſon to induce us, <hi>to wit, Beloved</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let us love one another, for love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God, and he that loveth not, knoweth not God, for God is love,</hi> Chap. 4.7, 8. It is therefore ſtyled <hi>the royal Law,</hi> James 2.8. Becauſe it cometh both expreſſely and eſſentially from God the Father, and from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings. Now in regard it is both the expreſſe command to love one another; and the eſſentiall and efficient worke of the Spirit of God for it both cometh of God, and God is love. And in regard that the end of the commandement is love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that the whole Law, <hi>to wit,</hi> that reſpects our neighbour is fulfilled in this, <hi>to wit. Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> and that this is that ſecond great commandement, and ſo like the firſt; as that <hi>he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>love God whom he hath not ſeen.</hi> Nor manifeſt himſelfe to be his Diſciple, nor indeed a true Chriſtian, See 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.20. &amp; Ch. 3.14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it neceſſarily followeth that ſuch who are Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and expect to be ſo accepted and accounted of either with God or men, ought to account themſelves moſt chiefly bound to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43990:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> this duty of love, and that to all the <hi>brotherhood,</hi> above all other duties commanded in the Law that concerns our neighbour. And that in regard that all other dutyes are inferiour, and <hi>leſſer matters of the Law,</hi> As tithing <hi>of Mint, Anniſſe, and Cumin</hi> was to the <hi>Jews,</hi> which yet <hi>ought to be done,</hi> provided that <hi>Judgement, mercy, and faith,</hi> which are the greater matters be not thereby neglected nor ſecluded; for this was in the Scribes and Phariſees a token of their hypocriſie; and how can we poſſibly excuſe our ſelves from the ſame charge, if by our ſtrivings and conteſts about inferiour outward circumſtantiall matters and things of God, as Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall matters and wayes of government and miniſtration?</p>
            <p>We neglect and hinder the growth of love and ſo of faith like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe which are the two eſſencialls and only infallible marks of our Chriſtianity; And on the contrary part doe thereby provoke one another to wrath and enmity, biting and devouring one another till we be conſumed, as is but juſt with God, becauſe we cannot agree but fall out by the way, and that about the way like unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward children who part themſelves into various pathes till they are be wildred and looſe one another and ſome themſelves and their poor ſoules. And conſidering alſo that all the ordinances of God, and the wayes of government, and all the miniſtrations and gifts of God, with all the miniſtrators whom he hath ſent, and ſet in his Church, yea all the inferiour commandements in the morral Law, with all the Prophets, Apoſtles, Scriptures both old and new, yea all the truths and doctrines or examples therein held forth, both concerning Judgements and mercies with all other wayes and means of grace. Are all but given and held forth to us through the neceſſary meanes, for this neceſſary end, <hi>to wit,</hi> The producing of <hi>love out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience, and of faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained.</hi> See 1 Tim: 1.5. From all which I make bold to conclude, that if we make not the obſervance and uſe thereof, as helps and means conducing to the acquirement and fulfilling of this end, but in our keeping of the leſſer we obſtruct the greater, yea and even the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine of all, And that which if attained would bring the leſſer with it; as a naturall fruit which is included in it, and cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be ſeperated from it; See 1 Cor. 13.</p>
            <p>Then without all queſtion or peradventure we quite pervert the end of all the commandements and meanes of grace that God hath appointed at leaſt ſo far forth as we uſe them ſo as hath been
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43990:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaid before; <hi>Making his commandements void, and of none eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct</hi> in our ſelves or others, <hi>through our owne traditions,</hi> for we thereby hinder both our ſelves and others from acquiring to the end of <hi>the holy commandements that are given unto us.</hi> By the keeping whereof we might <hi>be made partakers of the godly nature, love cometh of God, for God is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe things being generally aſſented too, as ſo I nothing doubt, but all that are Chriſtians i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deed, in the ſight of God, both doe and will aſſent with me thus farre at leaſt: and that they will agree to indeavour the acquirement of this bleſſed end, as in duty they are bound.</p>
            <p>I ſhall further propoſe thoſe means and wayes which as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive would ſtrongly conduce to the acquirement of this end, through the help of God, the which as I conceive are of abſolute neceſſity, and ſuch as without which there is little hopes of this Accordant, nor of keeping this commandement, <hi>in the keeping whereof, there is great reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Then I deſire as accounting it our duty, and the naturall product of true brotherly love, that we might pray one with, and for another, and each for all, <hi>that we might be healed,</hi> and our breaches repaired, and we united, and made <hi>of one heart, of one mind, and of one judgement, and that the ſame mind might be in us that was in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> This I doubt not but all that are godly will juſtifie, and own, and indeavour to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>actiſe but that we might doe it in faith, it is required that we <hi>go firſt and be reconciled to our brethren, and then come and offer our gifts,</hi> See Mat. 5.23, 24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Therefore it is deſired for this end, that we might have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip one with another, and each with any, both in publick and private, and that in all Gods ordinances, ſo as love requireth: ſo farre as poſſible, and convenient, as being all members of the ſame body; <hi>to wit,</hi> of Chriſt, and each of other; for how elſe is it ever poſſible that we ſhould be reconciled, if we meet not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether my if we receive not <hi>one another, even as Jeſus Chriſt hath received us to the glory of God the Father;</hi> See Rom. 15.7. &amp; 3. John 9.10. Mat. 9.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That inſtead of diſowning or excluding any that is known to be Godly, of whatever way, or Church they are of, either Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters or people, from the Lords Supper, or any other ordinance, they deſire to partake of. We might all be willing to invite each
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43990:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> other to any ordinance that Chriſt hath appointed for mutuall comfort and edification, where our ſelves are admitted &amp; owned as Godly, in caſe when any Brother ſhall have occaſion to ſojourn or be occaſionally amongſt us to hear the word preached on any other buſineſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And not only ſo as but barely to partake of the outward ordinances; But that each and all that in the judgement of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may be accounted brethren, might be owned as ſuch, and dealt with as ſuch, <hi>not in word only but in deed and in truth,</hi> in a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acticall manner in all theſe reſpects or in any other, as we doe with brethren that are of the ſame judgement and ſociety with us, as accounting it our duty both to watch over, and to exhort, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proove, admoniſh, comfort, reſtore and releeve; and all ſuch du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as need requireth in a brotherly way for his good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as we our ſelves would alſo be dealt with in the like caſe, for our ſoules health and benefit any wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For this we are comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded, <hi>Doe to all men as ye would they ſhould doe unto you, for this is the Law and the Prophets;</hi> But if to all men, much more to our brethren that in the judgement of charity are of the ſame body together with us, under Chriſt our Head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For if they be members though they are but <hi>feete,</hi> (the body walketh ſlowly if it wanteth feete, See 1 Cor. 12.21, 22. nay, If thoſe <hi>neceſſary members of the body</hi>) ſhould either be cut off, or it halteth on them, you know the charge, and how we are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to <hi>make ſtreight pathes for our feete, leſt that which halteth be turned out of the way,</hi> which ſhould <hi>rather be healed:</hi> I wiſh this text were better underſtood then I doubt it is by the moſt part, even of the Churches of Chriſt, See Heb. 12 12, 13, 14, 15. Such who halt betwixt two opinions, ſhould rather be healed, and have ſtreight paths made for their feete, then turned out of the way to the Kingdome of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the doores of fellowſhip and Chriſtian communion might be ſet as wide open as can lawfully be allowed, or as can be practiſed without breach of duty, and conſcience towards God; by building men up in their evill wayes and <hi>ſowing pillowes under all arme holes, healing their wounds ſlightly, and preaching peace, when there is manifeſtly no peace,</hi> and that for their owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43990:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For if the doores of Diſcipline and Chriſtian communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould ſhut out any of the elect of God, either from hearing of the word or Church communion for their ſoules health; or that they ſhould be offended through the Churches default, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad, yea whither they be weak or ſtrong, See (Ezek. 34) they ought not to be <hi>thruſt with the ſide or ſhoulder, nor puſht with hornes,</hi> But <hi>the diſeaſed</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſtrengthned,</hi> and <hi>the ſick healed,</hi> and <hi>that which is broken, bound up; and that which is driven away, brought home againe;</hi> and <hi>that which is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, ſhould</hi> even <hi>be ſought out,</hi> and recovered, and <hi>no force nor violence</hi> ſhould be uſed by any <hi>in ruling</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> leſt <hi>the great ſheepheard of the ſheep,</hi> who is not willing that <hi>the leaſt of his little ones ſhould periſh,</hi> ſhould <hi>require his ſheep at the hands of the ſheepheards,</hi> and ſo <hi>deſtroy both the fat and the ſtrong, and alſo feed them with judgement.</hi> See ver. 16 &amp; read alſo, Mat. 18.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. And how wiſely ought thoſe to <hi>walke, towards them that are without,</hi> who are <hi>the light of the world, and the ſalt of the earth;</hi> Mat. 5 13, 14, 15, 16. For if that ſalt which ſhould ſeaſon the world, yea, even them that are without, and ſo bring them in, ſhall make it ſelfe naucious and ſo unſavory in their conceit as that they will not come neer it, but abhorre and loath it, <hi>wherewith then ſhall the world be ſeaſ ned,</hi> even thoſe yet without; ſure they may periſh, for ſuch who are made unſavoury in their conceits, if the great ſheepheard doe not <hi>ſearch his ſheep, and ſeek them out;</hi> as Ezek. 34.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to this end it was leaſt the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould make himſelfe naucious and unſavory unto any at all; he <hi>became all things unto all men, that by all means he might ſave ſome,</hi> and made himſelf <hi>ſervant unto all, that he might winne the more; and hath alſo commanded us to be followers of him, even as he alſo was of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> charging us to <hi>give non offence neither unto Jew nor Gentile, neither to the Church of God, even as he pleaſed all men in all things, not ſeeking his owne profit, but the profit of others, that they might be ſaved,</hi> &amp;c. And this he accounted to be walking <hi>wiſely, toward them that are without,</hi> and the wiſeſt way of all other for the winning of them, and <hi>he that winneth ſoules is wiſe indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how much might be gathered and ſpoken from theſe texts of Scripture, to ſpur us on to a tender hearted and pleaſing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory, in offenſive carriage, not only towards brethren, but even
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43990:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> towards them that are without and at enmity with us! and how needfull it is even in theſe our dayes, for ingaging brethren unto ſuch carriage one towards another, how true is that propheſie, that <hi>the love of many ſhall wax cold, becauſe iniquity ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed,</hi> yet it is not ſaid, that the love of all ſhall wax cold, for ſome doubtleſſe ſhall <hi>continue to the end and ſo be ſaved.</hi> But oh how far are we off in theſe dayes from thoſe commands of Chriſt! <hi>Luke</hi> 6.35. to wit, <hi>But love ye your enemies, and doe good, and lend, looking for nothing againe, and your reward ſhall be great in heaven, and ye ſhall be the children of the higheſt, for he is kind unto the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and to the evill;</hi> But oh how little kindneſſe is in theſe dayes ſhewed even unto the good. But ſuppoſe there be ſome love and kindneſſe ſhewed to our friends and brethren of the ſame ſociety whereof we are: What thanks may we poſſibly expect for this, when the very <hi>publicans do as much as we?</hi> See ver. 32, 33, 34. And how farre are we off from obeying thoſe Important commands of Chriſt, verſe 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. To <hi>love our enemies and bleſſe them that curſe us, and pray for them that deſpightfully uſe us, and perſecute us,</hi> &amp;c. when we cannot love our brethren nor pray for them, ſo cordially as we ought, and only becauſe they are led and ingaged through difference of Judgement to vary from us in reſpect of Church-government and Diſcipline, and in ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward wayes and adminiſtrations, which differences amongſt us; can never be proved to be ſcandalous ſins, for which they ſhould be ſecluded and ſuppoſe them erroneous, yet they can never be prooved to be therefore hereticks, becauſe their different Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are onely about inferiour matters and circumſtantials, by any party, and therefore ought not to be rejected upon ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, nor ſeparated from, but invited to communion in any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance ſtate only, in caſe when known to be under ſome ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſin. All ſuch I ſay, as are known to be Godly and worſhippers of God, and ſo in the Judgement of charity, of the <hi>miſticall body of which Chriſt is the head.</hi> And this I deſi e might be taken notice of, that as no man can deny but that the greateſt latti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of love, is the moſt Chriſtian. So is the greateſt lattitude of charity alſo, for love and charity are the very ſame inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quality, according to the lattitude and meaſure of our love, ſuch is the lattitude and meaſure of our charity, either in judging of others, or in our carriage towards them in any reſpect.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43990:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>6. &amp; laſtly, And that which muſt neceſſarily be agreed on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this admittance, &amp; brotherly fellowſhip can be made tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all the ſeverall parties; Is, that this admittance and receiving one another as love requireth, might not be accounted as a ſin or ſcandall in them that do it, by any Church, or Chriſtian ſociety, whereof they are members, nor taken as an offence by any of their members, but the contrary declared from theſe precedent grounds and inducements. In caſe as hath been ſaid, that in the judgement of charity they be viſible members of Chriſt his miſticall body, yea whether they be, or be not for the preſent joyned with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y particular body, one more then others, becauſe ſome there are who through deſire of correſpondency with all, or any, ſo far as lawfull, and ſo far ſeeking the love of all, as not being willing to offend any, of whatever Judgement, or Church, or way they are found to be of, whoſe J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dgements or wayes are matters of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongſt the godly: there being Godly men of various <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſuch reſpects, whoſe wayes and practices are according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and this being granted and declared accordingly, this end in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, is halfe obtained. And this I dare undertak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that all this is no more then theſe commands require, as neceſſary duties for exemplification of our true Chriſtianity; and that ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by all the Saints unto all their brethren: as much as in them lyeth, as the providence of God ſhall give them abilities and opportunities.</p>
            <p>But leaſt any ſhould thinke me to intend the exalting of ſome one way, and to deſparage others, as being partially ingaged, and ſo through prejudicat conceits and apprehenſions of me, and of my ends herein, ſhould be offended with me; As I have therefore plainly declared what my ends are before I began, and then my grounds from Scripture, from which I nothing doubt, but by the operation of the Spirit of God it will evidently appear, that theſe ends are nothing, but what in bounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> duty, which we are mainly commanded and ought to practiſe, nor doe I much doubt but to make it good againſt al objections that can be offered on the other part, and to remove the ſcruples that may ariſe in the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of any that is a truly rationall conſciencious brother of what ever way or form of judgement that he may be of, if he be indeed a brother and member of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And further, I declare that though it were to be wiſhed that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43990:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> all that are of one heart, and of one judgement, in all fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls; were alſo one in all other reſpects, yet it is my opinion, that theſe diviſions are of the hand of God, who many times wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by contrary meanes; and yet by his wiſe ordering of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of things, the effect and product is the better and ſweeter, and the re-uniting ſo much the ſtronger, as I ſhall inſtance in ſome particulars: Firſt, you know it is the ſaying of Chriſt, that <hi>a Nation, or Kingdome devided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand,</hi> and therefore as it is alſo the pollicy of men to devide as much as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible where they deſire to reign; Even ſo I ſay, who knoweth but the Lord hath purpoſely devided us, leſt we ſhould have ſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome Arbitrary government according to the will of man, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to ſtop our ſettlement, and to weary us out, with our ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and conteſts amongſt our ſelves; both to weaken our power, and conceits of our own wiſdome: and to diſcover our folly and humble us, that ſo he himſelfe may have dominion over us, and be our onely Head and Lord, and that in every reſpect, as King, Prieſt and Prophet, and ſo have all the glory aſcribed unto him, and that by all his people; according to that propheſie, Iſa. 2:11, 12. &amp; ver. 17. <hi>to wit. The pride <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f men ſhall be brought low, and the haughtineſſe of men ſhall be abuſed, and the Lord only ſhall be exalted in that day.</hi> And as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Philemon</hi> concerning his ſervant <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> ſo we may well hope concerning our ſelves, <hi>That perhaps we are parted aſunder for a ſeaſon that we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive one another for ever,</hi> and be the more ſtrongly united, See v. 15. And it may be alſo, that it is very much to <hi>prove the natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our love,</hi> See Philip. 2.20. &amp; 2 Con. 8.8. &amp; 24. verſes. And <hi>that thoſe that are approved</hi> ſuch <hi>might be made knowne,</hi> for this is one expreſſe end wherefore <hi>there muſt be diviſions amongſt us,</hi> See 1 Cor. 11.18, 19. And the truth is, it hath much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved already the unnaturalneſſe of our love, but very little of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalneſſe; For what great proofe of our naturalneſſe in love can it be, to expreſſe our love to our brethren and friends of the ſame judgement and ſociety with us, this is not thanks worthy as hath been ſaid, from <hi>Luke</hi> 6.32. But if we can <hi>love the brotherhood</hi> that differ from us, and it may be ſpeak evill of us, and are ſo far our enemies as they would perſecute and deſtroy us; this is thankes worthy and will indeed prove, and demonſtrate the naturalneſſe of our love, yea even to the very conſciences of our enemies; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43990:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> be the greateſt meanes to turn their hearts, and win their aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and convince them of their ſin in being our enemies &amp; ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil of us, and ſo to re-unite us by an inſeperable bond of love and unity, that can never be broken or ſuch whoever upon whom it taketh not this effect, it will <hi>heape cole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of fire upon their heads, and the Lord ſhall reward and recompence us,</hi> If we for our parts ſhall performe our duties, (See alſo 1 Pet. 2.19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24, 25.) by owning them as we ought.</p>
            <p>And againe, By means of theſe diviſions and conteſts there is much more light and knowledge held forth, then could poſſibly have had occaſion to be knowne, or ſo much as diſcuſſed amongſt us; but we ſhould have gone blindly to worke, in all or moſt of theſe things conteſted about, in compariſon of what is now made manifeſt, both in reſpect of the temper of mens ſpirits which is diſcovered by their actings, and the danger we were likely to have fallen into, through Lordly and ridged arbitrary actings, in impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon mens conſciences things not convenient.</p>
            <p>And beſides, Theſe diviſions have manifeſtly been a means to provoke all parties <hi>unto emulation</hi> in one reſpect or other. See Rom. 11.14, 15. Reade theſe two verſes and you will know what I meane; For by theſe deviſions and ſtrivings many are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to a holy emulation, yea to emulate one another in holineſs and righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>And thus as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer then men, and the weakneſſe of God is ſtronger then men.</hi> Yea even thus, <hi>he catcheth the wiſe in their own craftineſſe,</hi> and maketh us fools, and lets us find it by experience, that we might be wiſe; he well knoweth that <hi>the ſpirit which dwelleth in us, luſteth to envy,</hi> and hath told us of it, and yet that <hi>if we have envying and ſtrife in our hearts, we ſhould not rejoyce,</hi> becauſe <hi>this wiſdom deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſuall, and deviliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he is glad to deal with us as children, (If we may ſo ſpeak after the manner of men) yea as with perriſh, fooliſh, weward, wilful &amp; ſtubborn children, to devide us that he might unite us, to let us quarrel, and ſtrive, and fight in a ſpirituall ſence, purpoſely to unite us the more ſtrongly, and to prove the naturalneſſe of our love and brotherhood, and our wiſdome, and temper, and ſtrength what it is, that we might know it our ſelves, even our own weakneſſe and folly, and that we are as yet but children, and unfit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43990:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> for governement, or to <hi>Reigne as Kings:</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For it is hereby manifeſt to us, by the practiſes of all, of every diviſion of us, that we would be partia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l to our own cauſe, and party, and principles, and that againſt all others, and not for them though acknowledged brethren, and Chriſtians in reſpect of fundamentalls. And ſo would neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate and inforce them to a complyance and conformity to our own particular principles, and practices, or elſe they muſt not expect any love, or favour, or kindneſſe, or help, or incouragement from us. And this I could manifeſt at large to be the preſent temper of the ſpirits of many, and that of every party, and how the ſeverall parties have ſome of them at leaſt been guilty of blood through their zeale and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity againſt the others; but it is ſo obvious, and ſo well known that I need not to demonſtrate the particulars thereof. But this I dare ſay, and juſtifie, that this ſort of <hi>zeale is not according to knowledge,</hi> nor according to love and Chriſtianity, and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence not <hi>according to Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who was ſo farre off from ſhedding the blood of his brethren (though they were <hi>enemies in their minds through wicked works) that he laid downe his life, and ſhed his owne blood for them.</hi> And even ſo ought we to be alſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>even to lay downe our lives for the brethren;</hi> And till this temper of Spirit be in ſome good meaſure found to be in us, we are not fit to rule or have the leaſt authority committed to us, for we are ſomuch under age, &amp; but in the minority of Chriſtianity, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſpoken to, nor accounted (<hi>ſtrong men,</hi> nor men at age, nor as yet at years of deſcretion) <hi>but as unto babes in Chriſt,</hi> who muſt therefore be <hi>kept as under tutors and governours till the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though it is a promiſe which we do and ought to expect, and to comfort one another with, that the Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall come with power, and that it is alſo juſtly to be expected to be neer at hand, and is in ſome meaſure already preſent, and ſome will needs be ſo forward as to <hi>take it by violence,</hi> and beat down all before them that ſtands in their way, yea will not much care to deſtroy their brethren in whom the King of Heaven is already in ſome meaſure, and ſo cut off them from living to ſee it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it in the power, who deſire it alſo as much as themſelves, but cannot accord to fetch it in by force of humane authority ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43990:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> defenſive whiles it is increaſing and growing within us by the force and power of the Spirit of God, nor is it lawfull to ſay that this temper of ſpirit cometh of God; <hi>it is not the perſwaſion of him that calleth us,</hi> to goe about to inforce conformity to our own principles, and to impoſe them by force upon our deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that are contrary minded; but this is certainly of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Antichriſt, which is long ſince come into the world; and yet this very temper of Spirit if power ſhould be put into our hands, would be found in meaſure, leſſe or more in any party of us.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore judge in our ſelves, whether we are any of us yet, come to yeares of diſcretion ſuitable for governement, whiles we are ſo partiall in our own cauſe and principles; <hi>ſhall he that hateth right, govern;</hi> ſaith the Scripture. Nay, if the power and Kingdome be already in the hand of Chriſt, and he giveth it to whomſoever he pleaſeth, can we expect to have it whiles in ſuch a temper of ſpirit. Nay, may we not rather expect that <hi>wiſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſhall have the rule and government over ſuch lewd ſons,</hi> that can never agree but are ready to <hi>bite and devoure one another</hi> at every advantage? Oh brethren conſider, and let us lay it to heart, and charge it home upon our conſciences betimes! for there it will fall heavy one day, and if we judge not our ſelves we ſhall certainly be <hi>judged and chaſtened of the Lord, that ſo we might not be condemned with the world,</hi> But if our maſter cometh and findeth us <hi>ſmiting of our fellow-ſervants: you know the place where we muſt have our portion.</hi> And if we poſſibly do not nor dare not, or cannot ſmite them hand or with the ſword, yet there is a ſmiting which is as bad, <hi>to wit, With the tongue,</hi> for it is compared to <hi>a ſword, or a ſharp raſor;</hi> And this kinde of ſmiting is too too frequent and common amongſt us, and ſheweth clearely that if power and commiſſion were in our hands, the other ſword would follow. Oh theſe things brethren we had need to repent and to humble our ſelves, and watch over our hearts, left he cometh and find us in ſuch a poſture of ſpirit! the danger is great, yea it is ſo much the greater as it is expected to be neer at hand. And therefore let us be exhorted by the Apoſtle, <hi>Speak not evil one of another brethren,</hi> &amp;c. Nor <hi>think not to eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we know theſe things, and that they are no other but the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43990:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> truths of God: Oh take heed that we let them not ſlip! but keep them applyed to our ſoules and conſciences till they reply to doe them. <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant whom his maſter, when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing, verily ſuch a ſervant ſhall be Ruler over all his goods.</hi> Read but Mat. 24. from 41. to the end, and conſider it ſeriouſly for it much concernes us in theſe latter dayes.</p>
            <p>And take notice of one thing, if we be indeed the people of God, we ſhall never <hi>ride on proſperouſly,</hi> but <hi>in the wayes of truth of meekneſſe and of righteouſneſſe,</hi> See Pſal. 45 for we muſt not proſper, but in the ſame way and manner that Chriſt hath led us, for this Pſalme is a propheſie concerning Chriſt and his Kingdom, who will not own us but in the ſame paths that he hath trod be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; Read it and compare it with our wayes and we need no more conviction.</p>
            <p>Oh how many is there in this generation <hi>that are pure in their own eyes, that yet are not cleanſed from this filthineſſe!</hi> (Pro. 30.12.14.) that is ſo farre contrary unto brotherly love, and meekneſſe, and of truth, and righteouſneſſe. Oh how ſad will it be with us if the Lord cometh and findeth us ſo doing! and in our envy and ſtrife, and not in that wiſdome that cometh from above, which is pure indeed and word, yea <hi>peaceable and gentle, full of mercy and of good fruits, without grudging, &amp; without hypocriſie,</hi> ſeeing <hi>the fruit of righteouſnes is ſown in peace, of them that make peace.</hi> James 3.17, 18. ſee alſo Ch. 4.11, 12. &amp; ver. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. And <hi>bleſſed are the peace-makers,</hi> Mat. 5. See there and conſider to what ſorts of people thoſe 9 ſorts of bleſſings do properly belong; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any of them proper for ſuch kind of poſtures of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as many of us are found in this our generation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> telleth us plainly (Ch. 1.26.) <hi>That if any man amongſt us ſeeme to be religious, and refraineth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this mans religion is vain.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle alſo Chap. 4.11. <hi>Speak not evill one of another bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, he that ſpeaketh evill of his brother and judgeth his brother, ſpeaketh evill of the Law, and judgeth the Law,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon is manifeſt becauſe the Law forbiddeth it, and commandeth love which is quite contradicted and judged by us, when we ſpeake evill one of another: And therefore let us lay it ſeriouſly to heart, and but conſider it, how apt we have been in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43990:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> theſe deviding times to ſpeake evill, yea and even the worſt that we can have any pretence for, one of another; how apt have we been to pick out the worſt, <hi>taking all in the worſer part, in the evil part,</hi> and whiſpering it out to the deſparagement one of another, by reaches, and jeeres, and reproaches, even running deſcant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faults or failings, and weakneſſes one of another moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harmoniouſly, and maliciouſly, making it the moſt part of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and eſteeming them beſt company who could caſt forth the pureſt jeeres and reaches againſt our brethren of any contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way: And who hath not been guilty in theſe reſpects? And how ſad is it that we have ſo little regarded the danger of theſe things? I mean of deſpiſing <hi>one of the leaſt of thoſe little ones that beleeve in Chriſt;</hi> See Mat. 18.10, 11. <hi>Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones; for I ſay unto you, that in heaven their Angells doe alwayes behold the face of my father which is in heaven. For the ſon of man is come to ſave that which was loſt.</hi> By which it is evident, that every one of thoſe little ones that beleeve in Chriſt hath an Angell of God, (as it were) ſtanding before God, in a continuall readineſſe to execute his commands in their behalfe, ſo that <hi>it were better for a man that a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the Sea,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore <hi>woe unto the world becauſe of offences,</hi> &amp;c. See ver. 6, 7, 8, 9. And it is certaine that Chriſt hath an eye upon them, who came on purpoſe to ſave that which was loſt, and therefore will certainly ſave them, and hath his Angels ready, <hi>and will avenge them ſpeedily, if they cry unto him,</hi> See Luke. 18.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Beloved brethren, I include my ſelfe as well as others under this guilt, and have been <hi>rebuked and chaſtened of the Lord for ſuch things,</hi> and therefore dare not <hi>Juſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my ſelf and condemn others,</hi> nor expect any other, but that whoever continue in ſuch practices ſhall ſmart for it one time or other, be they who they can, if they doe not repent. Will a father ſuffer his children to wrong, and bite, and devoure one another, nay his little ones eſpecially, and not whip them for it. And <hi>as a father pittieth his children, ſo the Lord pittieth them that feare him.</hi> Pſal. 103.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be objected, that this is ſo maine a cauſe of the differences amongſt us, that it will hardly ever be aſcented to by any party in regard that all their principles are quite contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory to the receiving of any to communicate with them in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43990:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sacrament of the Lords Supper, unles they be known to be of their owne way: and eſpecially ſtrangers, who ordinarily get letters of recommendations for this very purpoſe, or elſe they are not? ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And if every Miniſter or member of a Church, might bring in a ſtranger, meerly upon his own knowledge and acquaintance with him, and that without ſatisfying of the reſt of the Church, it would ſoon grow to that, that there could be no reſtraint nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline at all exerciſed in the Church, but all would be admitted that had any friend a member of a Church in the old promiſcuous manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To this I anſwer, Let it be conſidered, That the cauſe of the differences are not becauſe that any at all that are knowne to be Godly, are admitted to the Sacrament, nor the doores of fellowſhip ſtraitned on purpoſe, to keepe any of them out from any ordinance but to keep out thoſe who are ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or ignorant, and that chiefly for their own good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I anſwer, That I doe not propoſe it, that any ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, either becauſe they are Presbitterians, and ſo known to be, nor becauſe they are Independants, or Anabaptiſts, but becauſe they are known to be Godly: for there may be ſuch of any party <hi>crept in</hi> who are not Godly, but <hi>turne the grace of God into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and laciviouſneſſe, and denying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> See Jude 4. I doe not move to the receiving of any, but that are known to be Godly, of what ever forme or Church or way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I doe not move that every one might have liberty to invite another, but thoſe that are knowne and approved to be Godly, and judicious; For the younger ſort of profeſſors cannot be thought able to diſcerne, being but beginners; But ſuch are not fit to be accounted Miniſters, nor beare the office of Elders, or Deacons, that may not be truſted in ſuch a caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be objected that the wiſeſt may be deceived, whereas a whole Church might be more diſcerning and ſome or other may know them unfit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, if it ſo falleth out it is the fault and will be the deſparadgement of him that bringeth him in upon his owne Judgement, and it is nothing at all to the reſt of the Church: And if he have no ground ſo to judge of him, and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dmitteth him let him bear the blame, as may be thought fit, the Church is guiltleſſe.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43990:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be objected that it is a main principle in Church-pollicy, to admit none that are not polliticially incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into ſome Church or other, and that are willing to ſubmit and ingage to the diſcipline thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I anſwer, It is true, that it is an old and maine prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in Church pollicy, but I for my part could never learn from what Scripture ground it could be proved lawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. But am, and allwayes have been againſt it in my Judgement, ſince I firſt knew it to be their principle and practiſe, but ſhall be glad if any will inform me how it can be lawfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the precedent grounds of this diſcourſe, and moſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that command of the Apoſtle; <hi>Receive ye one another even as Jeſus Chriſt hath received you, to the glory of God the Father,</hi> ſee Rom. 15.7.</p>
            <p>Now if we doe not receive one another to the outward ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Chriſtian communion, which are all the glory that we can received and admit them too, how doe we follow Chriſt who hath received us to the glory of God the Father? which is the higheſt and greateſt glory that he himſelfe can have. And this his love to us hath ingaged him to, <hi>when as yet we were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it alwayes looked ſo like to the practiſe of <hi>Diotrephes, who loved to have the preheminence, and received not the Apoſtle John, nor the brethren,</hi> &amp;c. Inſomuch that theſe principles in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ingaged in a great meaſure to the very ſame practiſe, for if the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> yea or Chriſt himſelfe ſhould come amongſt us as ſo he doth ſometimes in his members, he could not be received till he firſt conforme himſelfe, both in judgement and practiſe, or profeſſe ſo at leaſt, and alſo ingage to ſubmit to the diſcipline, and ſo be under thoſe who are all under him, elſe he muſt not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate.</p>
            <p>But this I dare affirme, and have alwayes ſo accounted it as a dangerous thing, for any Church, or any part or member of a Church, <hi>neither to receive the brethren, nor ſuffer them that would,</hi> (See 3 John 9, 10, 11.) eſpecially conſidering there is no ground that I yet know of in all the Scripture for ſuch a policy, but is meerly invented to ingage or inforce men to their own principles, and practiſes, whether their judgements be convinced of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe thereof, yea or no, the which is not Chriſtian, it is not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43990:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> by our brethren, as we would that they ſhould doe unto us in the like caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be ſaid, if they be not incorporated with us, and ingage to the government of the Church, we have no power to exerciſe any authoritative diſcipline over them, nor doe we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our ſelves ingaged to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, The Church hath as much power from Chriſt, and is as much ingaged in duty to exerciſe it over any <hi>that is called a brother,</hi> and owned as a brother, as if they were ingaged and incorporated with them in the ſame Church, and this ought to be declared amongſt all the Churches, See Levit. 19.17. Mat. 18.15, 16, 17. and 1 Cor. 5.11, 12, 13. and 2 Theſſa. 3.6.14, 15.</p>
            <p>Now it cannot be denyed, but we ought to love and not hate our brother in our heart, but we cannot ſhew that we love him, if we doe not rebuke him, <hi>but ſuffer ſin upon him;</hi> And therefore it is ſaid, <hi>thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke him,</hi> which implyeth that no excuſe muſt ſerve our turne, as that he is not of our Church, or way, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or it belongeth to the Church he is of to deal with him this will not ſerve to ſhew our love to him, but rather that we hate him, See Lev. 19.17. So that all the injunctions that lye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, that ingage us to any duty to our brethren of the ſame Church, lye as clearly upon us, from this duty of love to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed unto all, or any whomſoever, that we account a brother ſo farre forth as we have abillity, and opportunity, yea though in ſome reſpects becauſe of differences in judgements, and ways they be really our enemyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will yet be objected that we have nothing to do with the members of other Churches in reſpect of diſcipline and governement, but it belongeth wholly unto them to admoniſh, rebuke, ſuſpend, and excommunicate as need ſhall require, and if they doe it not, it is their ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, It is their ſin if they doe it not, when they ſee cauſe for it. But if they doe it not, they ought to be admoniſhed of their duty, and neglect thereof, and if then they neglect any Church where he hath communicated, and ſo been owned as a brother may doe it, as to him and them, as after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition if he will not hear to ſuſpend him from any communion with them, as if be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere their own member; and that <hi>in the name
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43990:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and by his power and authority if there be ground in Scripture for what they doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will yet be objected that ſuppoſe they be not as yet of any Church, nor will not ingage to any party, how then can they be diſcipline if need ſhould require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If it may be conceived in the judgement of charity that any ſuch is a brother he ought likewiſe to be owned as a brother, by any Church where he is knowne as ſuch, and be admitted to all the ordinances. And where he is admitted in any or many Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es he is alſo ſubject to the diſcipline thereof, and cannot avoid it if he would, for he cannot avoid the Judgement of Chriſt, where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he dwelleth, or removeth, and if he ſtay amongſt them they may and ought to deale with him according as they do with bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and it will be as authoritative by the power of Chriſt as if he were a joynt member. For Chriſt will make good, and approve, and bleſſe any juſt miniſtration in his ſacred name (See Mat. 18.18, 19, 20.)</p>
            <p>And in my apprehenſion there it that are Godly, that are not yet joyned with any Church, ſave only in love, and private com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and that cannot yet reſolve to be joyned to any but the body-miſticall. And that becauſe their judgements are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ſome or other of each of their principles; and this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple laſt named is one of the greateſt obſtructions to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of any that I know of, being not grounded on Scripture but on meer humane pollicy, and being the moſt obſtructive to love and communion: which God hath ſo ſtrictly commanded and charged on us above all other duties as hath been proved. And it is well known that many would joyne themſelves to one Church or other, but for offending the reſt, and therefore they look for, and pray, and expect alſo through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>medy of God for a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement, that ſo they might joyne, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d give no offence, neither to Jew nor Gentile, nor to the Church of God;</hi> no not to thoſe of their own mind, in this reſpect of which there is many. And therefore this principle being unto generally agreed to be laid aſide would open door to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>full A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t, and that in a little time, through the bleſſing of God in all other differences about theſe inferiour matters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For by meanes of fellowſhip one with another. The Spirit of God co-operating amongſt us would bring us all to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43990:15"/> ſame judgement, whereas whileſt our judgements are different, it much cooleth and interpoſeth and obſtructeth our love and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall reſpects one to another, and many times produceth evill-ſpeaking, and reproaches, and diſdaining one of another, through our naturall infirmities, which is not a meanes to provoke unto love and good works, which we ought to uſe and continually practiſe, but the quite contrary even to wrath, and hatred, and enmity, and diſpleaſure, as it evidently appeareth by too much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, beſides what we know from Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> We ſhall not deny (ſome will ſay) to own ſuch for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren whom we know to be Godly, but we cannot own all to be brethren who are admitted to the Sacrament of the Lords-Super, eſpecially where it is promiſcuouſly adminiſtred, and how then can we communicate with them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were that leſſe in us then a juſtification of their male adminiſtration? which is quite contrary to our Judgements and Faith, <hi>and what ever is not of faith is ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I ſuppoſe it cannot properly be ſaid that either the Presbiterians, Independants, or Anabaptiſts, doe adminiſter it promiſcuouſly, but there is care taken that is be not adminiſtred to the ignorant or ſcandalous, or to ſuch as make not ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or other of the Chriſtian religion, leſſe or more, either in truth or hypocriſie. And ſuppoſe they miniſter Godly, that is, of larger principles for admittance then we, and in caſe we think him too large, we ought in the judgement of charity to ſuppoſe that his judgement leads him to it, and upon that account we may lawfully communicate with him if we judge him to be godly and ought to owne him, and if occaſion ſerve, communicate with him and the charge will lye at his owne doore, if he be in fault, and not at all on us who doe not by ſo communicating with him, and owning him, own all the reſt of which it may be we know but few, or it may be none at all, but are only invited by the Godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to partake with him; and it is he that adminiſtreth it, and and communicateth it to us, and if we ſhould deny being invited till we know all the reſt; it may be we ſhould never owne him as a Chriſtian whileſt we live, but by denying to communicate then, when invited, deny him to be a Chriſtian and Miniſter of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And ſuppoſe a Miniſter at his firſt coming to a Congregation,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43990:15"/> where the people are numerous that have formerly been received to communion by a precedent Godly Miniſter, ſhall ſuch a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter be in conſcience bound not to adminiſter the Sacrament, till he be ſo far acquainted with them as to know them to be free from ſcandal, and to have a competency of knowledge to examin themſelves, and to know the danger in caſe they receive unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily?</p>
            <p>Let any Chriſtian judge whether this were not too heavy a taske for a Godly Miniſter and in ſuch a caſe whether it might not ſerve to admoniſh them all in publique, to take care how they tempt God in medling with his ordinances, in ſuch reſpects, before they know how to examine themſelves, that ſo they may come preparedly, and diſcerne the Lords Body, and ſo not eate and drinke to themſelves Judgement. And whether ſuch a Miniſter is not cleared for his part, in caſe he ſo admoniſh them, or whether he muſt call them all into tryall and examination, before he may lawfully adminiſter the Sacrament, let wiſe men judge, whether the judgement of charity will ingage them to ſo heavy a task be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt admit them.</p>
            <p>And whether after telling them the danger, and inviting them to come to him, in caſe that any make doubt whether he be fit and able to examine himſelfe, that ſo he may receive it in faith and have benefit thereby; and he will be ready and willing to inſtruct and teach them what in him lyeth, and adviſe them for their good.</p>
            <p>But as for him what more can he doe in ſuch a caſe, doth not charity bind him to communicate with them, knowing nothing to the contrary but that they are ſutable and fitly prepared, being owned as ſuch, by his predeceſſor, think but of this Scripture, 1 Cor. 16.14. <hi>Let all your things be done with charity,</hi> and it will convince, for what can this Imply leſſe then that there muſt be an ingredient of charity viſible in us in all our actings and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, that we undertake in the name of God for edification, now <hi>charity ſuffereth long, and is kind, it envyeth not, it thinketh not evill, it beareth all things, beleeveth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things;</hi> Inſomuch that if a man had all other gifts of the Spirit, and wanted but this one ingredient of charity, in the exerciſe thereof, and that alſo in viſibillity as held forth with them, or as the efficient cauſe of the exerciſe and uſe of all the reſt,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43990:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> he is accounted as nothing by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> meaning that all the other gifts are as it were uſeleſſe, and unprofitable, for edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church, if this be wanting as a chief ingredient for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring, and reliſhing, and ſeaſoning of them, it being as ſalt for ſeaſoning and reliſhing all unſavorie meats which elſe are nauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and unfit for food for our naturall bodyes, See 1 Cor. 13. &amp; Mat. 5.13. &amp; ſee Coloſſ. 4.6. <hi>Let your ſpeech be alwayes with grace, ſeaſoned with ſalt, that ye may know how ye ought to anſwer every man,</hi> See alſo Mark 9.49, 50. &amp; Lev. 2.13. By ſalt can be nothing elſe meant but a cordiall affection of love or charity, and that held forth in viſibillity for ſavouring all out actings and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations in the name of God.</p>
            <p>For if ſuch who are the only ſalt of the earth doe not keep themſelves ſavoury, but become naucious and unſavourie to thoſe whom they ought to ſeaſon; how ſhall they ever ſeaſon them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made themſelves unſavoury, and wherewith ſhall themſelves be ſeaſoned, to make them reliſh better for the ſeaſoning of others and eſpecially of the world, when they will not heare them. For how ſhall they enlighten the world or ſalt or ſeaſon them? In caſe they will not come neer them; becauſe they have made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unſavoury as to them at leaſt in their apprehenſions, though they be not ſo in themſelves? for by that means they put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of all poſſibility of doing them any good, and therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> became <hi>all things unto all men that by all means he might ſave ſome,</hi> this was his wiſdome, and ought to be ours, and wherein we faile of this and walke by ſome other rule, we are doubtleſſe ſo farre off from the wayes of God, and the wiſdome of his holy Spirit, (See for this, Acts 21.24, 26.) how <hi>Paul</hi> acted as if the Jewiſh ceremonies had not been aboliſhed, and how <hi>he circumciſed Timotheous becauſe of the Jews,</hi> Acts 26.3. And how <hi>he became as without law, to them that were without law, that he might win them that were without law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider theſe things ſeriouſly, and lay them in the ballance of the Sanctuary, and ſee if they will not more then counterpoiſe all that can be objected, why we ſhould not communicate in the moſt diſtinguiſhing ordinances, with all whom we know to be Godly, and yet ſtill continue to differ in our practices as our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments lead us till our judgements are convinced, and reconciled, that ſo our practices alſo may be the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43990:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nor can it be ſaid that we juſtifie, ſuch in their male admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, by our communicating with them our practiſe being publickly known, to be the contrary in our own ſocieties.</p>
            <p>And conſider alſo, whether this is not the likelieſt and neereſt way to a full Accordance, and reconcilement in all our differences that are amongſt us. And whether keeping ſeperate and at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance can in any poſſibillity produce Accordance. And whether our duty of love can be performed without this fellowſhip one with another, See 1 John 1.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it is a thought which I feare ariſeth in the hearts of many: That their brethren of other Judgements and wayes from them are ſo ſtiffe ſpirited, and ſo malignant towards us, that if we ſhould invite them to communion, and ſhew them never ſo much love and reſpect, they would not heare us nor accept our motion, but deſpiſe our offer and invitement, and it may be take it as though we were convinced that our wayes are not good, and that we are ready to forſake them upon that account, and to join with them, and approve of their wayes as better then ours, the which we are unwilling they ſhould thinke of us, till it be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I anſwer, We muſt and ought to do our duty to them whom we account brethren, what ever they thinke, or how ever they take it, if our conſciences be clear in the ſight of God, we ſhall have peace with him, though when we <hi>ſpeake of peace</hi> to our brethren, <hi>they are bent for war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if our brethren take it in the <hi>evill part,</hi> and deſpiſe our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and invitement, the fault is theirs in the ſight of God, and if they be ſtiffe ſpirited and malignant againſt us, let us take care that we give them no cauſe, but doe our beſt indeavour to remove all <hi>ſtumbling blocks,</hi> and offences that are on our parts, and the Lord will bleſſe us and hear our prayers, and reward our <hi>worke, and labour of love that we have ſhewed to his name,</hi> and for ought we know he may turne their hearts to be otherwiſe minded, then we expect, It may be our ſtiffeneſſe hath been a cauſe of theirs, and theirs of ours. And ſo likewiſe may our yeelding and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth of love and condeſcention provoke them to doe the like.</p>
            <p>And therefore let no excuſes re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard or hinder our ſpeedy indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for mutuall Accordance. But let us make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſineſſe,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43990:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> and that as a matter of greateſt importance, and concernement to us, yea as a matter of life and death, leſt the Lord cometh and findeth us ſmiting our fellow ſervants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And give me leave a little, to inculcate and beat it home to our very conſciences. Conſider it ſeriouſly, did not the Lord himſelf inculcate this command upon his holy Diſciples, and that over and over again, with argument after argument, and command af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter command? and ſhall we think it needleſſe in this frozen age? Nay, Did he make it his buſineſſe, when he was ready to leave them, and to give it forth chiefely as his will and teſtament, and ſhall not we think it worthy to be made as our buſineſſe, and that of greateſt concernement in this our age, and generation, becauſe <hi>the love of many waxeth cold</hi> already? However in this treatiſe I ſtudy brevity, expecting that men better able, will make it their buſineſſe; And yet if I ſeem to repeat and fall on againe with the ſame Scriptures, it is to preſſe them further. Conſider therefore thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>A new commandement I give unto you, that ye love one another as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one another,</hi> John 13.34.</p>
            <p>Conſider it I ſay, It is the commandement of Chriſt to all ſuch as are, and would be accounted, and knowne by all men to be his Diſciples, which is the promiſe annexed, verſ. 35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye have love one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the meaſure of this love is expreſſed in the latter part of the 34. ver. <hi>to wit, As I have loved you, that ye alſo love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this meaſure of love is further explained, as to the latitude and extent thereof, in reference to the ſame command, <hi>to wit,</hi> John 15.12, 13. <hi>This is my commandement that ye love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as I have loved you,</hi> And how is that? See verſ. 15. <hi>Greater love hath no man then this, that a man lay downe his life for his friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this is the true and proper meaning of Chriſt without any miſticall dark ſence. See how the ſame Apoſtle, that loving Diſciple, who is therefore truly called the beloved Diſciple, or <hi>the Diſciple whom Jeſus loved,</hi> as though in compariſon he had lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him. And certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is, that though he love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them all; yet he loved <hi>John</hi> with a more peculiar tranſcendent affection,
<pb facs="tcp:43990:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> then any of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reſt, and chiefly becauſe that his doctrine of lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and his commands thereof, took more impreſſion in him then the other Diſciples, and the love of God, and the love of the brethren tooke more place in his heart, as ſo it is manifeſt in his Epiſtles, and Goſpel, by his treating more and more fully of love then all the other Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Con.</hi> From whence I may gather by the way, That they that love moſt, are the moſt beloved, and the moſt bent to the preſſing and inculcating, and communication of the doctrine of love, unto their brethren.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Con.</hi> And that they whomſoever that cannot cordially em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and receive this doctrine, are not cordially embraced and received of Chriſt, and that in reſpect of the meaſure of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diallity.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Con.</hi> Look how much more cordially we embrace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his doctrine of love, by ſo much the more cordially we ſhall be, and are embraced, yea loved and received of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And thus much by the way.</p>
            <p>Now for the proper extent of the manner and meaſure of this duty of love, See 1 John 3.16. <hi>to wit. Hereby perceive we the love of God, becauſe he laid down his life for us, and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not ſufficient to love <hi>in word, and in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngue only, but it muſt be in deed, and in truth,</hi> (verſ. 18.) eſpecially if we would know that we are of the truth, and that the love of God dwelleth in us, and would have our hearts aſſured before him, (See ver. 17.19.) we muſt not ſhut up our bowels of compaſſion if we have this worlds good, and ſee our brother hath need, for in ſuch caſe, there is no appearance or manifeſtation that the love of God abideth in us.</p>
            <p>No, <hi>he that loveth not his brother abideth in death. And whoſoever hateth his brother is a murtherer, and we know that no murtherer hath eternall life abiding in him</hi> See verſ. 14.15 Read this Chapter throughout, and Ch. 4. wherein it is ſo evident that the Apoſtle preſſeth this duty of love as the great and chiefeſt, duty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt, and that without which we cannot poſſibly be aſſured that we are yet <hi>paſſed from death unto life,</hi> nor that God loveth us, and we him, nor that we <hi>keep his commandements, and doe thoſe things that pleaſe him,</hi> nor that we know God, or <hi>dwell in
<pb facs="tcp:43990:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> him, and he in us,</hi> nor that we <hi>ſhall have boldneſſe in the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> neither can our <hi>feare</hi> that <hi>hath torment in it</hi> be caſt out, nor can we prove our ſelves to be true men, but lyars, becauſe it is impoſſible that <hi>he who loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeene, ſhould love God whom he hath not ſeen. And this commandement have we from him, that he who loveth God ſhould love his brother alſo,</hi> See Chap. 4. <hi>And this is the meſſage that ye have heard from the beginning, that we ſhould love one another,</hi> Chap. 3.11. See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 1 Tim. 1.5. <hi>Now the end of the commandement is love out of a pure heart, and a good conſcience, and faith unfained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why is this called the end of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement? but becauſe that <hi>he that hath loved another hath fulfilled the Law,</hi> for no man can love his brother but he loveth God, nor any man love God, but he will alſo love his brother, and <hi>upon this hangeth the whole Law, and the Prophets, to wit,</hi> To <hi>love God above all, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, Becauſe if this love be in us in perfection as it ought, the naturall product of it will be ſuitable both in reſpect of our duties to God, and to our neighbours, for <hi>love worketh no evill againſt our neighbours,</hi> much leſſe againſt God, See 1 Cor. 13.</p>
            <p>Now this main duty of love and the meaſures and neceſſity of it being ſufficiently proved, and that from ſuch authority as no Chriſtian can for ſhame gainſay it, or oppoſe it in the leaſt. I ſhall proceed to anſwer ſome Queries that may be made.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Query.</hi> The firſt and chief whereof is, And who is our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſo we may know whom we ought to love with ſo vaſt and boundleſſe an affection, as that for their ſakes if need ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire we ſhould be willing even to lay down our lives for them, and much more our goods and eſtates? as ſo the command is clear, and full, and without exception.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, I ſhall firſt ſhew whom we ought to account as brethren, and ſuch to whom we owe this meaſure and manner of love. And ſecondly, I ſhall ſhew whom we ought to account our neighbours, and we ought to love them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All ſuch ought to be owned and accounted our brethren whom we know to be profeſſors of faith in God, through our Lord Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, and to be worſhippers of God, and that they doe not live in any ſcandalous known ſin, nor doe not hold and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43990:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> maintain any manifeſt convicted error after due admonition, nor are not willfully ſchiſmaticall, nor imperiouſly proud and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, and this I beleeve no rationall and ſober Judicious Chriſtian will deny.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſidering that of neceſſity we muſt but judge according to the rules of charity, in regard we have not any rules of certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but ſuch as wherein we may be deceived, and it is far better to be deceived by extending our charity to the loving of ſuch as doe not properly deſerve it, then through meer uncharitableneſſe to deny ſuch love and brotherly reſpect, as our duty requireth to all the brother-hood, and ſo to give them Juſt cauſe to be offended with us; for it is dangerous to offend one of the leaſt of thoſe little ones that beleeve in him, See Mat. 18.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſidering the length and breadth of that love, or charity which cometh of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For if the love of God be <hi>ſhed abroad in our hearts</hi> really as it ought, it is ſo charitable that it thinketh no evill, Nay, <hi>it bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all things, beleeveth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things,</hi> (See 1 Cor. 13 5.7.) Nay, <hi>it ſuffereth long, and is kind,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 4. It taketh not <hi>all things in the evill part, it judgeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before the time, it quencheth not the ſmoaking flax, nor break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bruiſed reed,</hi> and ſuch like, many Scriptures I might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, but theſe I hope are ſufficient for any that underſtand them, and the latitude of their ſence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſidering the abſurd unſavourineſſe of judging or diſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any as brethren of whom we know ſo much as hath been ſaid before of their profeſſion and practiſe, but have nothing to the contrary whereof to accuſe them. And they that are or ſhould be <hi>the ſalt</hi> of <hi>the earth,</hi> ſhould by all means take heed they looſe not their <hi>ſaltneſſe,</hi> or become unſavoury to whom they ſhould ſeaſon, for who then ſhall ſeaſon them? that ſo they might be able, or in a capacity to ſeaſon others. See Mat. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. &amp; Mark. 9.50. <hi>Have ſalt in your ſelves, and have peace one with another:</hi> ſaith our bleſſed Saviour. And by this ſalt is meant the affection of love and charity, for without the exerciſe of theſe, though we <hi>had the tongue of men and Angells,</hi> and ſuch other gifts reckoned up by the Apoſtle, (1 Cor. 15.) yet we ſhould be ſo unſavourie if together with thoſe gifts we did not exerciſe <hi>charity,</hi> us that we ſhould <hi>profit nothing,</hi> nor ſeaſon any of thoſe with whom we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43990:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> but ſeem as it were naucious unto them, all other gifts would do us no good for edifying of the Church, if Charity be wanting in us, or if we doe not exerciſe them in a way of charity, and as mixed with charity and powdred with the affection of love; the which (as ſalt to our corporall meat) m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>keth it ſavoury and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning to the hearts of others, but if we ſtep aſide out of the ways of charity, and cannot hold that forth, as having it really in us, and acting by it and in it, It is becauſe we have but little of it in our own hearts, and then who can expect to be ſeaſoned by us, See 1 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.31. &amp; Chap. 13 1, 2, 3. and compare the ſence whether it be not ſo as hath been ſaid, <hi>Covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, and yet ſhew I unto you a more excellent way.</hi> that is to ſay, get abundance of charity ſo as to exerciſe thoſe gifts in the way, and ſhew a manifeſtation of charity, or elſe they are all worth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for edifying of the Church, but <hi>like ſounding braſſe or a tinckling cimbal,</hi> in which there is not much for the uſe of edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. No No, <hi>knowledge indeed puffeth up, but it is love that edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> See 1 Cor. 8.1.</p>
            <p>But it may yet be demanded how this Scripture is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, how love edifieth, conſidering love is an internall grace, as ſo alſo is faith, which cannot be communicated to others from us, but are gifts of God.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, It is love which edifieth, becauſe love is the efficient cauſe of all Spirituall miniſtrations that are effectuall for edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is the fountain and ſpring from whence doth flow forth ſuch cordiall expreſſions as are effectuall for edification. It is of the eſſence of the Spirit of God, <hi>he that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that when love ingageth us, or is the efficient cauſe of any expreſſions or miniſtrations, it may truly be attributed to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God as the chief cauſe of ſuch miniſtrations, and they are certainly efficacious either as <hi>the favour of life unto life, or of death unto death,</hi> as the words of God, nay, as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>the words that I ſpeake unto you they are ſpirit and they are life.</hi> See John 6.63.</p>
            <p>So words that come from the Spirit are Spirituall words, they are cordiall, fervent, earneſt, and powerfull words. They are words of life and power for edifying in the faith, <hi>and provoking unto love and good works.</hi> And therefore when men are acted and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43990:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> exerciſed from a root and principle of love, they are properly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and exerciſed by the Spirit of God; And it is more proper to ſay ſo of them, then that they exerciſe their gifts, for it is their gifts, <hi>to wit,</hi> of the Spirit, and Faith, and Love, which exerciſe them. They are but the inſtruments, God is the Agent. It is God that granteth them <hi>according to the riches of his glory, to be ſtrengthned with might by his Spirit in the inner man, that Chriſt may dwell in their hearts by faith, that they being rooted and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in love, may be able to comprehend with all Saints what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height, and to know the love of Chriſt which paſſeth knowledge, that they might be filled with all the fullneſſe of God,</hi> See Ephe. 3.16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>See here what large requeſts the Apoſtle putteth up, and that in few words for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and in how compleat an order. For though he aſcribeth the originall of all ſtrength and might in the inner man, to the Spirit of God, as the prime efficient cauſe thereof, and the moſt immediate, as ſo it is, yet as next immediate, and as inſtrumentall cauſes whereby he work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th immediately, he joyneth faith and love as co-operative, (and if I may ſo ſay) as co-eſſenciall cauſes of all ſpirituall power and ſtrength, for work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us up, and making us capable and comprehenſive to <hi>be filled with all the fullneſſe of God;</hi> for unleſſe Chriſt dwelleth <hi>in our hearts by faith, and that we be rooted and grounded in love,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>be able to comprehend with all Saints,</hi> as verſ. 18. Nor can we <hi>be filled with all the fullneſſe of God,</hi> as ver. 19.</p>
            <p>And conſider alſo how no leſſer mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures of the Spirit, and Faith, and Love, will ſerve the turne to fulfill the deſires and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of the Apoſtle on their behalfe, but that they might be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all the fulneſſe of God, which might teach us not to be content with any poor meaſures of his holy Spirit, But to <hi>covet earneſtly even the beſt gifts,</hi> and the largeſt meaſures that are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable, and that we are capable of. For he that hath bid us co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet them and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke them, can eaſily give them, and make us ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable and comprehenſive of them <hi>through faith and love which are in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the ſpirit worketh faith, and worketh by faith, to make us capable of diſcerning all ſpirituall things, for they being invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as God himſelfe cannot be ſeene with bodily eyes, but only through an eye of faith, And <hi>faith worketh by love,</hi> and alſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43990:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> love, See 1 Theſſ. 1.3. &amp; Gal. 5.6. For what we cannot ſee through faith and apprehend to be lovely, we cannot poſſibly love it (I meane it) of ſpiritualls, and inviſibles. And therefore it followeth, that if we have but a little faith, a dim-eyed faith, we have alſo but a little love, and a little deſire after ſpirituall things, but are poor, and content alſo to remain poor in all ſuch reſpects, (See Rev. 3.7, 8.) But God hath <hi>choſen the poore of this world, rich in faith, to be heirs of his Kingdome.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> alſo, his eyes were <hi>upon the faithfull in the Land; and upon the excellent that they might dwell with him.</hi> Pſal. 101.6. But he was a man <hi>after Gods own heart,</hi> where ſhall a man be found now in this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that maketh his choice after the ſame rule, to make them his aſſociates, and <hi>companions, and delight, and his counſellers,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> did, See Pſal. 16.3. &amp; James 2. &amp; 2, 3, 4 5. And why is it? but for want of faith, which worketh by love, and worketh love to the choiceſt objects that are the moſt lovely, and alſo the moſt loving, for there is a reciprocacy in this reſpect, in the ſight of God, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
            <p>But if it be conceived that many doe in a great meaſure as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did, I ſay let us take the Apoſtles counſell who beſeecheth in ſuch a caſe, to <hi>increaſe more and more,</hi> (See 1 Theſſ. 4, 10.) which ſheweth that he would not have us reſt content with any poore or ſcant meaſures, but to be preſſing forwards, towards perfection in ſuch reſpects wherein we can never goe beyond the mark that is ſet us, and therefore it is that the Apoſtle biddeth, <hi>ſeeing we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and are zealous of ſpirituall gifts, ſeeke that we may excell to the edifying of the Church,</hi> See 1 Cor. 14, 12. From which it is evident that we may and ought to ſeek, that we might excell, provided it be not to make our ſelves famous in the eyes of men, but <hi>that our conſciences may bear us witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt,</hi> that our end is mainly <hi>for the edifying of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this end can never ſway us to any great zeal, unleſſe our love to the Church ingage us to it, and the love of Chriſt muſt as it were conſtraine us, as it did the Apoſtles, yea and even Chriſt himſelfe, now where love engageth us it will not pervert the end of ſuch ordinances which Chriſt hath left us for our edification, to make them as ſtumbling blocks, and as rocks of offence to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct our communion, whereby we have occaſion for edifying one another in faith and love.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:43990:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But it will rather <hi>caſt up and prepare the way, and remove the ſtumbling blocks out of the way of his people,</hi> See Iſa. 57.14. That ſo all the elect and beloved of God may accord with us, and come in and conſecrate with us in all Chriſtian communion and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly fellowſhip, for it is the nature of love to unite cordially, for love is in the heart, and therefore it was that in the primative times, they that beleeved were of one heart, and of one mind, and the ſucceſſe was, they had all things common.</p>
            <p>Now it is well known that cordiall love cannot be enforced, but muſt be induced, we cannot cudgell it into the hearts of any; God is the Author and Fountaine thereof, nor can our ſeperation and keeping a part ever induce it, but it muſt be induced through loving and kind fellowſhip, and communion together, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that God hath commanded fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>Conſider ſeriouſly this Text of Scripture, what it clearely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth, I ſpeak it as to wiſe men (as the Apoſtle did) to judge what I ſay of it, <hi>to wit,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Wherefore my dearly beloved, fly from idolatrie. I ſpeak as to wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay. The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the blood of Chriſt. The bread which we break is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt. For we being many are one bread, &amp; one body, for we are all partakers of that one bread.</hi> From all which give me leave to aske you, doth not his bidding us fly from idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, imply that we may idolize the bread and wine, as ſo not only the Papiſts do, who account it the reall body and blood of Chriſt, which <hi>they heare</hi> us doe, <hi>and muſt containe till all things be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> But when we make account as if the bread and wine after conſecration or bleſſing of them had any vertue in them to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh our ſoules to eternall life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich were only left us as outward ſignes to be eate and drunke in remembrance of him, and that by his body, the Church, ſo that when they gave thanks or bleſſed the bread and wine, they did not pray that the bread and wine might be bleſſed to the people for their Spirituall nouriſhment, But they prayed that the communion and fellowſhip of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body might be bleſſed, that is to ſay, that their union and fellowſhip together might be a meanes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their edification, and that is faith and love, and ſo might grow up together, and hold cloſe to the <hi>Head from which all the body being knit together, by joynts and bands having nouriſhment miniſtred, might increaſe with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43990:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> the increaſe of God,</hi> See Coloſſ. 2.19. And this is the end for which this Sacrament was ordained; <hi>to wit.</hi> for our edification in faith and love, and that by having communion with Chriſt who hath promiſed his preſence amongſt us, in caſe we follow his ſteps and walke in love as he hath loved us, and ſo obey his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement and love one another, owning one another, and having fellowſhip one with another, and diſowning none that are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his body, but receiving all his members, even as <hi>he alſo hath received us to the glory of God the Father:</hi> Then I ſay he will doubtleſſe own us and be preſent with us, and <hi>ſhed his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve abroad in our hearts,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d build us up in faith, yea the whole body toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>till we come to be tall,</hi> and ſtrong, ſo as to <hi>aske what we will,</hi> (with a joint conſent) <hi>and it ſhall be given us,</hi> whereas whileſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, how can we expect that our prayers ſhould be heard whiles we are not reconciled to our brethren which he hath bid us <hi>do firſt</hi> even as <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his brethren, Gen. 43 5. <hi>Ye ſhall not ſee my face except your brother be with you,</hi> even ſo ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Goe firſt and be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift, and leave thy gift on the Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar</hi> till then; as if he ſhould have ſaid, doe not expect thy gift ſhall be accepted, till you be agreed, you are both my ſons, I cannot indure you ſhould live at variance, come not here, doe not expect to ſee my face till you be agreed, I will not own thee in ſuch a poſture of ſpirit, thy brother hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt thee that is contrary to love, go and agree with thy brother, as I have commanded thee, and then thou art welcome; <hi>Aske and ye ſhall receive, ſeeke and ye ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened unto you, and by this all men ſhall know that ye are my Diſciples, if</hi> (you make it appear) <hi>that ye love one another:</hi> Whereas on the other part, how can any man thinke you are my Diſciples, or have any love to me, or I to you, if ye cannot love and own, and have fellowſhip together one with another as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ought, and as love ingageth where it is cordiall, and not in word, and tongue only, but indeed &amp; in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uth. Nay, how eaſie is it for any man to prove and that from Scripture, that whoever denyeth this Chriſtian-fellowſhip with his Chriſtian brethren <hi>is yet in darkn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he goeth?</hi> See 1 John 1.6, 7. &amp; Mat. 5.23, 24 &amp; Mat. 7.7. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Dil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilah</hi> could ſay to <hi>Sampſon, How canſt thou ſay I love thee, when thy heart is not with me?</hi> See Judges 16.15.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43990:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And this we may juſtly ſay to our ſelves, how ſhall we ſay for ſhame, or how can we think that we <hi>love God,</hi> if we have not a care to <hi>keep his commandements?</hi> And can we keep his commandements and not love our brethren? or can we ſay we love them and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree with them but fall out by the way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be objected, ſuch and ſuch are our brethren, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y will not goe our wayes, we are in wayes that we know to be right, and they are in by wayes, and are bewildred, and will not be perſwaded, and how can we help it, we are forced to leave them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If they be our brethren, and that we ſee them out through weakneſſe, and that we thinke our ſelves <hi>ſtrong, we ought rather to bear the infirmities of the weake then to pleaſe our ſelves,</hi> leſt our father be angry with us, and ſay, why did ye leave my little children, and overrun them in the dark night, whileſt they cannot ſee but be bewildred? and ſo ſend us back to fetch them home, and not ſuffer us to reſt or come within doors, till we bring them with us, and it may be whip us alſo for leaving them at all without a guide. It will not ſerve to excuſe us, to ſay our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were wilfull and pettiſh, and would go their own wayes, or go none at all, they being but children No, a father will not looſe his children, and danger to have them caſt away, becauſe they are weak and pettiſh, but will rather ſay, why did ye not rather turne back and bring them to me that I might have corrected them, &amp; taught them better, but you muſt leave them in danger, and in an angry mood, could ye not have ſpoke them faire and in a loving way perſwaded them as children.</p>
            <p>Beloved brethren, Conſider it ſeriouſly for there is no father can be ſo choice and tender hearted towards his little children, as the Lord is choice and tender hearted towards his little ones as hath been ſhewed before, and though he will not deny us to be his children but own us as ſuch in an overly-way, yet he will not welcome us, nor lodge us in his boſome with ſuch ſweet embraces and kiſſes of love, nor entertaine us familiarly, ſo as to know his counſells, and his mind, and ſecrets, till at leaſt we have indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what in us lyeth to perſwade our brethren to come along with us, and that in love and meekneſſe as a nurſe uſeth to doe with children. And when we have uſed the means &amp; cannot do it, yet let us never ceaſe to pray to our father, ſaying, father perſwade them
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43990:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> thou art able to doe it though we cannot. <hi>The Lord perſwade Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth to dwell in the tents of Shem. And then Canaan ſhall be his ſervant.</hi> And doubtleſſe it is already upon the hearts of many of the faithfull ſervants and meſſengers of God, both to pray, and preach for this Accordance, though with little hopes of obtaining there deſires becauſe they ſee ſuch ſtiffeneſſe in the hearts of the people, and averſeneſſe to it, and in ſome of their miniſters which is ſad and lamentable, that the leaders of the people ſhould cauſe them to erre, and to remaine ſtiffe againſt the expreſſe commands both of God the Father, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and of his holy Apoſtles, and Prophets, &amp; not to ſtoop at all, nor ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nor their wayes and judgments, but as aſcribing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves infalibillity of Spirit as if they could not erre, See 1 Cor. 13.12.</p>
            <p>Conſider I beſeech you whence this ſtiffeneſs ariſeth, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not manifeſt that it ſpringeth from the root of pride and ſelf love, and conceits of our own wiſdome above others of our brethren, that yet in account with others are as wiſe as we, and it may be much wiſer; and that alſo in the ſight of God. But as I ſaid before, when <hi>the leaders of the people cauſe them to erre.</hi> The caſe is lamentable and very dangerous, leſt <hi>they that are led of them be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtroyed,</hi> See Iſa. 9.13, 14, 15, 16, 17. And let me ſay to ſuch ſtiffe ſpirited leaders of the people: If they will but looke in the bottome of their hearts they ſhall certainly finde there a root of pride, and ſelfe-love, to be the originall fountain from whence this ſtiffeneſſe ſpringeth and groweth up. And they cannot but know who it was that called ſuch like men <hi>blinde guides for ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out a gnat, and ſwallowing a cammel, and for omitting of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, mercy, and faith, and tithing of Mint, Anniſſe, and Cumin,</hi> as hath been ſpoken to before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will yet be objected, ſhall not we be going on, and preſſing forwards, but we muſt ſtay for them that will not pace with us but make ſtands by the way, and are not ſatisfied that we goe the right way, and therefore will not forward in the beſt and neereſt pathes which we know are ſuch, and they will not be perſwaded, and ſome are not ſo able, and zealous, as yet to goe forward ſo faſt as we, and ſhall we ſtay for them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If they be our brethren we may well ſtay a while to perſwade them, and tell them what way our father directed us to goe, and we cannot be ſure our ſelves that he hath ſo directed us,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43990:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> but we can eaſily ſhew it them, and make it manifeſt. But if it be their weakneſſe and want of zeale, let us take them by the hand as little children, and help them forward, and go their pace, and not leave them behind, as amongſt the wolves; our Father will be angry if we over-run them, and whip us for it. For this is not <hi>like as a nurſe cheriſheth her children,</hi> as the Apoſtle dealt with the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2.7, 8. It is not ſo gentle, nor ſo <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate, for he being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffectionately deſirous of them was willing to impart, unto them not onely the Goſpel, but even his owne ſoule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were deare unto him,</hi> and ſo would alſo <hi>Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> whom in ſuch reſpects we ought to follow, and if we will indeed preſſe forward unto perfection, let this be our marke and then we ſhall not over-run our little brethren whiles they are in non-age, no though they be a little froward and pettiſh like children, nor though they think themſelves wiſe and ſtrong, and yet we know them to be weak and fooliſh; For if we know them to be ſuch, we know them alſo to be but children and babes in Chriſtianity in compariſon with others of a riper ſtanding, for becauſe they are weake, or froward, pettiſh, or fooliſh, ſhall we be ſo likewiſe? Do we not ſhew our ſelves alſo to be but children in Chriſtianity as well as they? and are we not ſo far ſhort of the Apoſtles practiſe, and reſolution before named? It were but a bad nurſe that ſhould ſo carry towards little children. Compare but ſuch practices with the Apoſtles, and it will convince. And if we take in alſo that undenyable example of the Lord himſelfe, how he dealt with <hi>Iſrael</hi> who were <hi>a ſtiffe-necked people,</hi> and how <hi>long he ſuffered their manners in the wilderneſſe,</hi> See Deut. 32.11, 12, 13, 14. How he dealt with them as an Eagle, and bare them on his wings, and lead them in the way through a deſart wilderneſſe, feeding them with oyle, and milke, and butter, and honey ſo as they wanted nothing, neither did he leave them nor forſake them, for all their frowardneſſe, till they firſt forſooke him, and ſerved other gods; though he ſaid of them, verſ. 20 <hi>They were a very froward generation, children in whom was no faith.</hi> And ſure there cannot be much faith in us, whileſt we have ſo little love, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſo little to obey his firſt and great commandement, wherein all the whole laws of God, and the ends of them are ſo clearely contained, and comprehended, ſo as in obeying them, we cannot chooſe but fulfill them all, as hath been proved at large from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43990:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And let us conſider alſo another Scripture or two, <hi>to wit,</hi> Eph. 5.29, 30. <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ever yet hated his own fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it, even as the Lord doth the Church, for we are members of his body, of his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, and of his bones. And he gave himſelfe for it, that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the word, that he might preſent it to himſelfe a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh,</hi> See ver. 25, 26, 27. Now if Chriſt ſo loved and hath owned his Church as members of his own body, and fleſh, and bones, and hath given himſelfe for it, and made it his buſineſſe to ſanctifie and cleanſe it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if we ought to <hi>be followers of God as deare children, and to walke in love as Chriſt alſo hath loved us,</hi> As verſ. 1, 2. Then doubtleſſe we ought alſo to make it our buſineſſe, and our maine buſineſſe of all other, to preſent all the members of his body, the Church per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, we being alſo members one of another, (See Chap. 4.25.) as a perfect and glorious Church, without ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing. And to that end we muſt <hi>let all bitterneſſe, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evill-ſpeaking, be put away from us, with all mallice. And be kinde one to another, tender-hearted, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving one another, even as God for Chriſts ſake, hath forgiven us,</hi> See Chap. 4.31, 32.</p>
            <p>The Lord open our underſtandings to conſider, and diſcerne how much theſe ſacred words of truth and faithfullneſſe, concern us all in theſe dayes of ours, for his great names ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43990:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
